<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-14T15:49:34-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Micah Potts, Engineering Manager At Large</title><subtitle>This is the place for me to talk about the industry and my place in it.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Believe?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/14/the-ted-lasso-of-ems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Believe?" /><published>2023-04-14T12:20:53-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-14T12:20:53-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/14/the-ted-lasso-of-ems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/14/the-ted-lasso-of-ems.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ted-lasso-believe-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Believe!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
While filling out a recent job application (one of so, so many), I was asked, “What’s your leadership style?” Unlike the countless other times, I’ve been asked this question today my mind jumped to, “What’s manager-speak for ‘I’m kind of the Ted Lasso of Engineering Managers?’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why. Because, like him, I’m not afraid to look a little goofy to help others reach success. Because I’m not afraid of asking questions, even if everyone else in the room is. And if I’m being honest, because like him, in the wrong environment my leadership style can be misconstrued as I don’t know what I’m doing. (Also because “manager-speak” is not my first language.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I think “The Lasso Way” looks like for Engineering Management:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rule--1-respect-those-around-you&quot;&gt;Rule # 1: Respect those around you.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Here’s my personal motto: Always try my best to walk into an organization with a healthy respect for the state of the application and organizational culture. Understand that the choices everyone has made up to that point were made with the best intentions. My role as engineering leader is to respect those choices, even if they differ from those I would have made. Without this baseline of respect, we can’t begin to move forward.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you join an organization, it is your duty to learn from those around you and learn about the history of the choices they made before suggesting changes. To me, this is of the utmost importance. There is no right way to run an engineering organization because engineering organizaitons are PEOPLE and not code. There are best practices, yes, but walking into the (virtual) room, dramatically swooshing everything off of the (virtual) desk, and screaming, “I know best!” is certainly not the way to build trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rule--2-be-curious&quot;&gt;Rule # 2: Be curious.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it a point to be curious about the people you work with. Curious about how they work best, what brought them here, and their goals. Build a relationship. Build trust. After a time, use that trust-based relationship to make personalized and actionable suggestions for the team. Make iterative and measurable changes in the direction everyone wants to go. We’re in it together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rule--3-no-wonderkids&quot;&gt;Rule # 3: No “Wonderkids”.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes an organization is in such dire straights that they believe the desk-sweeping caricature (a “wonderkid,” if you want to keep up the Ted Lasso parallels) is the actual role of an engineering leader. In my experience they are often early-stage startups who think an Engineering Manager will solve all their problems (we can certainly try!) immediately (we certainly cannot!). In those environments, curiosity and deference to the people and processes in place can be seen as a lack of action, not a way to set up long-term success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those cases, forced, sweeping changes can cause an engineering team to fall apart. Burnout. Loss of velocity. Unhappiness. Even mass exodus. No one changes overnight. (No matter what the diet industry wants you to think!) As humans, we work best when we make small, lasting changes. And work towards a long goal. Together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is to be done? Of course, the easy answer is to ask honest, thoughtful interview questions that help you see between the lines of the Job Description and get to the real expectations for a role. (Yep, I just solved it all in one sentence! You’re welcome.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re done laughing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that it is easier said than done. Many organizations aren’t aware that each person in their interview loop can have a different idea of what an Engineering Manager should do! The questions that will give you a great response with one team member can be enough to get you kicked out of the interview loop with another. Pondering this has led me to believe that the solution needs to start on the other side of the fence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hiring for an engineering leader, please ensure everyone on the team is aware of and committed to what you are looking for. And when I say everyone, I truly mean everyone. From the CTO to the newest Junior Developer. If you decide you need a player/coach, everyone commits to that. If you decide you need a people-focused manager, again, everyone commits. Make sure your Job Description states it too. It will help you get what you want, and the exercise will help you understand your organization’s needs. And please, leave the magical thinking at the door. Real and lasting change takes time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>